Finding Aid for the Mctyeire-Baskervill Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Mctyeire-Baskervill Papers
1848-1963
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0283
1.68 linear_feet
From The Sullins Reflector, Vol. 6, No. 3 (Nov. 23. 1942):
Mrs. Janie Baskervill, "Our Friend," Former Dean of Girls Dies at Sullins, November 5
Gave Generously of Her Talent; Interested in Community Affairs
"Mrs. Janie McTyeire Baskervill, one of the most widely known and most dearly loved women in educational circles of the south, died in her apartment at Sullins College, Thursday, November 5, at 5:30 a.m., after an illness of eight weeks. Funeral services, in charge of Dr. J. Stewart French, assisted by Dr. J.E. Hicks and Dr. H.H. Thompson, were held at the home of Dr. and Mrs. W.E. Martin on Glenway avenue, Friday, November 6, at 10:30 a.m. Burial was made in Mount Olivet cemetery, Nashville, Tennessee.
"Mrs. Baskervill, daughter of the late Bishop Holland Nimmons McTyeire and Amelia Townsend McTyeire, was born April 8, 1862, in Mobile, Alabama. During her early childhood she moved to Nashville, Tennessee, where her father was president of the Vanderbilt University board and senior bishop of the Methodist Church. It was he, Bishop Holland Nimmons McTyeire, who prevailed upon General Cornelius Vanderbilt, noted New York philanthropist, to establish the university.
"Her husband, the late Dr. William Malone Baskervill who died in 1899, was head of the department of English University and was one of the founders of the Southern Association of Colleges.
"Since coming to Bristol as dean of women at old Sullins College, she had been active in community affairs for many years. With her daughter, Mrs. William E. Martin, and Dr. Martin, Mrs. Baskervill moved to Woman's College in Montgomery, Alabama, and served there as dean of women. For a great many years she held the position as dean of girls and social director at Sullins College.
"Mrs. Baskervill showed deep interest in women's clubs of Bristol and offered much to their organization. She was a member of the Woman's History Club, Gibbon History Club, and the Ann Carter Lee Chapter of the U.D.C..
"Mrs. Baskervill has had charge of promoting the annual Red Cross Drive at Sullins College for the past several years, and has always been very enthusiastic and highly successful with this project.
"Surviving are two daughters, Mrs. William E. Martin of Bristol and Mrs. Elizabeth Baskervill Wall of Bedford, Virginia; one son, William Malone Baskervill of Baltimore; one step-son, John Adams Baskervill of Nashville; seven grandchildren, Mrs. Garland Osborne and Mrs. Raymond Bailey of Bristol, Mrs. Francis Cash of Cincinnati, Ohio, William Thomas Martin of New York, N.Y., Misses Dorothy, Evelyn, and Jane Baskervill of Baltimore, Maryland; and five great-grandchildren."
From Alumnus Magazine Vol. XXVIII, No. 2 (November, 1942), p. 2:
Mrs. Baskervill Dies
"Mrs. Janie McTyeire Baskervill, one of the most widely known women in Southern educational circles, died on November 5, at Sullins College, Bristol, Virginia, after an illness of eight weeks. She was buried at Mt. Olivet Cemetery, Nashville.
"Mrs. Baskervill, who was dean of Sullins College for many years, came to Nashville from Mobile, Ala., in her early childhood. She was the daughter of the late Bishop Holland Nimmons McTyeire, for many years President of the Vanderbilt University Board of Trust and Senior Bishop of The Methodist Church. Her husband, the late Dr. William Monroe /i.e. Malone/Baskervill, who died in 1899, was head of the Department of English at Vanderbilt University and was one of the founders of the Southern Association of Colleges.
"Going to Bristol as dean of women at old Sullins College, Mrs. Baskervill had been active in community affairs of the city for many years. With her daughter, Mrs. William E. Martin, and Dr. Martin, Mrs. Baskervill moved to Woman's College in Montgomery, Ala., and served there as dean of women. For years she held the position as "dean of girls" at the present Sullins College,
"Mrs. Baskervill is survived by two daughters, Mrs. William E. Martin, A'02, of Bristol and Mrs. Elizabeth Wall, Ax'07, of Bedford, Va.; one son, William Malone Baskervill, Ax'10, of Baltimore; one stepson, John Adams Baskervill, Lx'06, of Nashville; seven grandchildren and five great-grandchildren."
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  333 items, including 113 holograph letters, 45 typed originals, 70 carbon or typed copies, 1 manuscript copy, 1 holograph note, 1 post card, and 2 telegrams. The correspondence is largely comprised of the incoming letters of Holland Nimmons McTyeire, Jamie McTyeire Baskervill, and William Malone Baskervill. 73 items are addressed to Holland Nimmons McTyeire, 82 to Janie McTyeire Baskervill, and 72 to William Malone Baskervill. Also included is a folder of correspondence to and from Devereux Lake, concerning the "Golden Link" (their wives) between Bishop McTyeire and Commodore Vanderbilt.
  - Alexander, Gross (?) to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 9 Sept 1911 (Box 1)
  - Allen, James Lane to William Malone Baskervill (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Atkins, K.C., and E.W. Moore to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 3 Nov 1887 (Box 1)
  - Baird, Donna to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 19 Mar 1939 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, M.J. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 26 Sept 1896 (Box 1)
  - Barnard, Edward Emerson all to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (4), 18 Sept 1899, 3 Nov 1899, 28 Aug 1922, 12 Sept 1922 (Box 1)
  - Barnard, F.A.P. to C. Vanderbilt (1), 29 June 1876 (Box 1)
  - Barnard, Horace to C. Vanderbilt (1), 15 May 1882 (Box 1)
  - Barton, W.P. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 8 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Barton, W.P. to G.B. Baskervill (1), 15 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Baskervill, Janie McTyeire to Mr. White (1), June 1900 (Box 1)
  - Baskervill, Janie McTyeire to Devereux Lake (13), 31 Mar 1933, 22 Nov 1938, 9 Jan 1939, 14 Apr 1939, 22 Apr 1939, 21 June 1939, 1 Aug 1939, 1 Sept 1939, 21 Nov 1939, 29 June 1940, 29 Dec 1940, 7 June 1941, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Baskervill, Janie McTyeire to Hill Turner (1), 1 Mar 1939 (Box 1)
  - Baskervill, Janie McTyeire to Mr. Vanderbilt (1), 28 Mar 1935 (Box 1)
  - Baskervill, Janie McTyeire to my dear sister (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Baskervill, William Malone to John Tigert (1), 27 Nov 189O (Box 1)
  - Bell, T.P., and I.J. Van Ness to Sirs (1), 17 Feb 1897 (Box 1)
  - Black, M.M. both to William Malone Baskervill (2), 5 Sept 1899, 15 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Aileen to Dr. Kuhlmann (1), 29 Nov 1950 (Box 1)
  - Blake, William K. both to William Malone Baskervill (2), 13 June 1878, 15 June 1881 (Box 1)
  - Bolling, W.T. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 21 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Boyle, Virginia Frazer both to William Malone Baskervill (2), 17 Jan 1899, 15 June 1896 (Box 1)
  - Bradshaw, Margaret both to William Malone Baskervill (2), 4 Sept 1897, 12 Dec 1899 (Box 1)
  - Brahham, William C. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 29 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Agatha to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Brown, O.E. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 1 Nov 1930 (Box 1)
  - Cable, G.W. to Mr. Gilder (1), 28 Dec 1887 (Box 1)
  - Cable, G.W. to William Malone Baskervill (2), 2 Mar 1889, 23 Oct 1896 (Box 1)
  - Callaway, Morgan Jr. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 22 May 1895 (Box 1)
  - Callaway, Morgan Jr. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 17 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Calvert, Mary R. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 18 Feb. 1928 (Box 1)
  - Calvert, P.R. to Mrs. A.M. Tigert (1), 16 Feb 1923 (Box 1)
  - Calvert, P.R. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 16 Feb 1923 (Box 1)
  - Candler, W.A. to J.D. Hamilton (2), 28 May 1917, 6 June 1917 (Box 1)
  - Candler, W.A. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 12 May 1932 (Box 1)
  - Carlisle, James H., David Duncan, Whitefoord Smith, W.W. Duncan, P.A. Du Pre, Charles F. Smith, and J.A. Gamewell to William Malone Baskervill (1), 11 June 1878 (Box 1)
  - Carmichael all to Devereux Lake (3), 10 Aug 1939, 10 July 1939, 22 Apr 1940 (Box 1)
  - Chappell, James E. both to Devereux lake (2), 12 May 1939, 21 Apr 1939 (Box 1)
  - Cheatham, H.C. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 31 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Clary, J.D. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 19 Nov 1897 (Box 1)
  - Cole, Whitefoord R. Jr. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 2 Dec (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Martha to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Martha to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 30 Aug 18-- (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Martha to Mary (1), 2 July -- (Box 1)
  - Dandridge, Mrs. D. to Sir (1) (Box 1)
  - Deems, Charles F. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 1 Aug 1876 (Box 1)
  - Deems, Charles F. to F.A.P. Barnard (1), 30 June 1876 (Box 1)
  - Dempsey, Elam F. both to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 27 Aug 1941, 2 Sept 1941 (Box 1)
  - Denny, Collins to J.D. Hamilton (1), 1 May 1917 (Box 1)
  - Denny, Collins to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 30 July 1935 (Box 1)
  - Drake, E.S. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 23 Oct 1896 (Box 1)
  - Duncan, W.W. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 23 Nov 1887 (Box 1)
  - Du Pre, D.A. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 8 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Edwards, John E. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 6 Dec 1887 (Box 1)
  - Emerson, William C. both to William Malone Baskervill (2), 10 Feb 1897, 9 June 1897 (Box 1)
  - Farish, Hunter. D. all to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (9), 11 Mar 1934, 6 Jan 1938, 14 Jan 1938, 20 Jan 1938, 2 Feb 1938, 24 Feb 1938, 8 Mar 1938, 18 July 1938, 19 Aug 1938 (Box 1)
  - Field, Nora Nimmons both to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 1 Feb 1936, 11 Feb 1936 (Box 1)
  - Fraley, C. Louise to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 29 Oct (Box 1)
  - Frantz, W.A. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 14 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Galloway, Charles B. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 1 Aug 1896 (Box 1)
  - Garland, J. Powell to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 22 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Ginn, Edwin all to William Malone Baskervill (3), 20 Aug 1887, 17 Dec 1887, 24 Dec 1887 (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, J.D. College of Bishops (1), 26 Apr 1917 (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, J.D. to Bishop Candler (1), 5 June 1917 (Box 1)
  - Harris, J.H. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 31 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, James A. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 18 Feb 1897 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, James A. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 10 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Haygood, A.G. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 25 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Hedges, S.B. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 12 May 1897 (Box 1)
  - Henneman, John B. all to William Malone Baskervill (3), 28 Feb 1896, 11 Feb 1897, 23 Dec 1897 (Box 1)
  - Hodges, Louise T. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 27 Feb 1896 (Box 1)
  - Hohlfeld, A.R. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 2 Aug 1900 (Box 1)
  - Hollahan, R. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 19 Nov 1888 (Box 1)
  - Hoss, E.E. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 7 Apr 1905 (Box 1)
  - Hulme, William H. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 10 Dec 1899 (Box 1)
  - Humphreys, M.W. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 23 May 1887 (Box 1)
  - Jackson, N. Baxter to Devereux Lake (1), 15 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Joynes, Edward S. both to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 1 Sept 1901, 3 Jan 1904 (Box 1)
  - Kelley, D.C. all to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (3), 26 Feb 1883, 17 Feb 1886, 20 Feb 1886 (Box 1)
  - Kinosuki, Adachi(?) to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 28 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Kirkland, J.H. to J.J. Tigert (1), 14 Sept 1898 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (13), 6 Jan 1939, 16 Jan 1939, 18 Jan 1939, 2 Feb 1939, 19 Apr 1939, 27 Apr 1939, 17 May 1939, 19 June 1939, 29 June 1939, 22 Aug 1939, 16 Nov 1939, 14 June 1940, 24 June 1941 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to Hill Turner (6), 14 Mar 1939, 7 Apr 1939, 17 Apr 1939, 29 Apr 1939, 9 May 1939, 11 Aug 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to James E. Chappell (4), 19 Apr 1939, 28 Apr 1939, 10 May 1939, 15 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to Woodall Rogers (2), 19 Apr 1939, 10 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to J.J. Tigert (6), 1 May 1939, 10 May 1939, 16 Aug 1939, 23 Aug 1939, 16 Nov 1939, 23 Apr 1940 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to J.P.W. Brown (1), 10 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to Baxter Jackson (1), 10 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to James B. Stahlman (1), 11 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to Eldon Stevenson (1), 11 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to O.C. Carmichael (2), 17 June 1939, 1 Aug 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to W.H. Witt (2), 19 June 1939, 26 June 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to J.T. McGill (1), 30 Dec 1942 (Box 1)
  - Lake, Devereux to Edwin Mims (1), 26 July 1944 (Box 1)
  - Lanier, Clifford to (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Lanier, Mary D. to William Malone Baskervill (2), 8 Oct 1896, 12 Oct 1896 (Box 1)
  - Lanier, Mary D. to W.B. (1), 19 Oct 1896 (Box 1)
  - Lanier, Mary D. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 2 Nov 1901 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, J.W. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 25 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Macarthur, James to William Malone Baskervill (1), 4 Nov 1898 (Box 1)
  - Mahue, R.H. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 23 Nov 1887 (Box 1)
  - Manly, Louise to William Malone Baskervill (1), 18 Feb 1897 (Box 1)
  - Mann, J.E. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 1 Nov 1887 (Box 1)
  - Marshall, C.K. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 25 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - McCabe, W. Gordon to William Malone Baskervill (1), 5 Feb 1888 (Box 1)
  - McGill, J.T. to Devereux Lake (1), 23 Dec 1942 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to Amelia Townsend McTyeire (1), 14 July 1859 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to Mr. Townsend (1), 28 Apr 1866 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to C. Vanderbilt (7), 21 May 1873, 22 May 1873, 31 July 1873, 24 Nov 1873, 9 Jan 1874, 31 Mar 1874, 5 Mar 1888 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to Mary A.E. Green (1), 6 Apr 1878 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. memo (1), 15 Aug 1879 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to William Malone Baskervill (5), 9 May 1881, 21 May 1881, 28 May 1881, 28 May 1881, 8 June 1881 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to Brother Pike (1), 23 Mar 1883 (Box 1)
  - McTyeire, Holland N. to E.M. Rossiter (1), 16 Apr 1888 (Box 1)
  - Meek, B.F. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 19 Apr 1886 (Box 1)
  - Mims, Edwin to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 10 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Moody, J.A. to (1), 29 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Newell, J.F. to William Malone Baskervill (2), 29 May 1896, 10 Feb 1897 (Box 1)
  - Newton, J.C. Calhoun to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 8 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - O'Howell, D.C. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (2), 25 Oct 1887, 28 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Page, Thomas N. to R.W. Gilder (1), 22 Dec 1887 (Box 1)
  - Parker, Lucy P. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 5 Nov 1926 (Box 1)
  - Parker, Mary E. both to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (2), 9 Oct 1885, 17 Feb 1886 (Box 1)
  - Paterson, C.A. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 21 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Redd, John W. both to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 21 Dec 1901, 22 Jan 1902 (Box 1)
  - Ross, Charles H. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 17 Apr 1897 (Box 1)
  - Rossiter, E.M. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 13 Apr. 1888 (Box 1)
  - Russell, H.E. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 6 Oct 1896 (Box 1)
  - Scales, Henry M. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 17 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Scott, F.N. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 10 July 1897 (Box 1)
  - Seals, T.A. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 24 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Sharp, Robert to William Malone Baskervill (1), 20 Mar 1897 (Box 1)
  - Shepard, Elliott F. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 14 June 1878 (Box 1)
  - Shepard, Elliott F. to Mrs. Crawford (1), 10 Sept 1888 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Charles Forster to William Malone Baskervill (3), 24 Nov 1896, 11 Feb 1897, 1 Jan 1898 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Charles Forster to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 7 Sept 1899, 3 Jan 1902 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Eugene A. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 11 Jan 1874 (Box 1)
  - Stahlman, James G. to Devereux Lake (1), 13 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Steel, S.A. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 2 Sept 1911, 13 Jan 1931 (Box 1)
  - Stevenson, Eldon to Devereux Lake (1), 15 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Stewart, John H. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 24 Jan 1874 (Box 1)
  - Stewart, Kate Louise Zimmerman to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Sullivan, W.T.J. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 21 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Sweat, Harriet T. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 25 Feb 1886 (Box 1)
  - Taliaferro, Mary Scott Venable to William Malone Baskervill (1), 18 Feb 1897 (Box 1)
  - Teague, Oscar, A.H. Wilson, G.J. Nunn, James A. Chiles, and O.C. Kelley to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 10 Oct 1899 (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Maurice to William Malone Baskervill (2), 19 Mar 1887, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Maurice to Mr. Gilder (1), 21 Dec 1887 (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Maurice to J.J. Tigert (1), 8 Sept 1899 (Box 1)
  - Tigert, Amelia McTyeire to W.F. Tillett (1), 6 July 1916 (Box 1)
  - Tigert, Amelia McTyeire to J.H. Kirkland (1), 6 July 1916 (Box 1)
  - Tigert, John J. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (6), 31 Dec 1934, 24 May 1935, 5 Dec 1939, 9 Jan 1940, 18 Aug 1941, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Tigert, John J. to Devereux Lake (6), 26 Apr 1939, 11 May 1939, 22 June 1939, 19 Aug 1939, 9 Nov 1939, 26 Apr 1940 (Box 1)
  - Tigert, John J. to Harvie Branscomb (1), 22 Nov 1950 (Box 1)
  - Tillett, W.F. to Amelia. M. Tigert (2), 26 June 1916, 14 Feb 1923 (Box 1)
  - Tillett, W.F. to J.D. Hamilton (2), 28 June 1916, 25 July 1916 (Box 1)
  - Tillett, W.F. to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (3), 17 Feb 1923, 23 May 1927, 12 Nov. 19-- (Box 1)
  - Turnbull, William to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 11 Feb 1876 (Box 1)
  - Turner, Hill to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (4), 21 Feb 1939, 27 Feb 1939, 6 Mar 1939, 24 Apr 1939 (Box 1)
  - Turner, Hill to Devereux Lake (3), 6 Mar 1939, 24 Apr 1939, 6 May 1939 (Box 1)
  - Vail, Henry H. both to William Malone Baskervill (2), 16 June 1897, 26 June 1897 (Box 1)
  - Van Cleve, Mary to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 10 Oct 1926 (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Cornelius to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (7), 17 Mar 1873, 31 Mar 1873, 26 May 1873, 9 June 1874, 15 June 1874, 13 July 1874, 2 Dec 1875 (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Cornelius to D.C. Kelly (1), 24 Mar 1874 (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Cornelius II to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (5), 7 Aug 1877, 4 Feb 1879, 24 Feb 1879, 16 May 1882, 2 Mar 1888 (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Cornelius II to E.H. East (1), 27 Mar 1889 (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Frank A. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (12) (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Frank A. to Amelia Townsend McTyeire (1) (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, William H. all to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (14), 11 Oct 1875, 24 Feb 1877, 7 Mar 1878, 19 Sept 1878, 13 Nov 1878, 21 Nov 1878, 23 Mar 1879, 15 July 1879, 2 Feb 188O, 22 Apr 1880, 10 Jan 1881, 20 Jan 1881, 26 Oct 1881, 26 Nov 1883 (Box 1)
  - Vincent, John H. both to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (2), 5 Oct, 5 June 1900 (Box 1)
  - Wall, Elizabeth Baskervill to Edwin Mims (1), 4 Oct 1943 (Box 1)
  - Webb, John M. all to William Malone Baskervill (4), 17 May 1886, 14 Feb 1897, 16 Feb 1897, 5 May 1897 (Box 1)
  - Weber, W.L. to William Malone Baskervill (1), 23 Oct 1897 (Box 1)
  - West, Olin Jr. to Alexander Heard (1), 26 Mar 1963 (Box 1)
  - Williams, Amicus W. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 25 Oct 1887 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, A.H.D. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 18 Nov 1887 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, A.W. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 18 Nov 1887 (Box 1)
  - Winchell, A. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 21 July 1876 (Box 1)
  - Witt, W.H. to Devereux Lake (1), 23 June 1939 (Box 1)
  - Worcester, E.D. to Holland Nimmons McTyeire (1), 7,Dec 1883 (Box 1)
  - Illegible signature all to William Malone Baskervill (3), 27 Apr 1886, 6 Jan 1888, 1 May 1897 (Box 1)
  - Lacking signature, to Janie McTyeire Baskervill (1), 11 Nov 1899 (Box 1)
  - Lacking signature, to J.W. Sewell (1), 13 July 1900 (Box 1)
- Papers of Holland Nimmons McTyeire (Box 2)
  - Newsletter addressed to and apparently published in the Southern Christian Advocate, headed "Reliable News from Nashville" and signed "H. N. McTyeire.", 6 March 1862 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter addressed to and apparently published in the Southern Christian Advocate, headed "Letter from the Country" and signed "M.P.", 12 February 1863 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletter addressed to and apparently published in the Southern Christian Advocate, headed "Letter from the Country" and signed "M.P.", 26 March 1863 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletter addressed to and apparently published in the Southern Christian Advocate, headed "Letter from the Country" and signed "M.P.", 11 June 1863 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 5 items relating to publication of H.N. McTyeire's book History of Methodism by Southern Methodist Publishing House (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 2 lists of licenses and certificates in H.N. McTyeire's hand (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Licence to perform weddings, Mobile, Alabama, 3 February 1848 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Holograph will of Holland Nimmons McTyeire with typewritten copy, 28 June 1881 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Holograph will of Holland Nimmons McTyeire with typewritten copy, 25 August 1884 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Holograph will of Holland Nimmons McTyeire with typewritten copy, 29 July 1885 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Vanderbilt University Papers (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Manuscript indenture between V.U. and Ward Seminary (6 pages), 30 June 1888 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - List of Exchanges drawn upon W.H. Vanderbilt, New York, by Bishop H.N. McTyeire (2 pages, manuscript), undated (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Typed copy of V.U. (i.e. Central University) Board of Trust resolution accepting gift of C. Vanderbilt, 26 March 1873 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Board of Trust reorganization report, signed by secretary (2 copies), 20 June 1888 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - White River Annual Conference of Methodist Episcopal Church South, approval of action of V.U. Board (1 page, manuscript), December 1888 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - V.U. Board resolution in appreciation of H.N. McTyeire, after his death (2 pages, manuscript), 15 February 1889 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - 5 resolutions, written in pencil on slips of paper, mostly dating from after McTyeire's death, undated (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - McTyeire family history (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - 3 pages from McTyeire family Bible, recording births, marriages, and deaths, 1795-1871, copied 1886 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - 4 manuscript pages recording Nimmons and McTyeire family births, marriages, and deaths, 1790-1876 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - "Notes on My Visit to Barnwell..." by John J. Tigert IV (5 page carbon copy), 23 May 1935 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - "Inscriptions on the graves in the family cemetery of the McTyeires at Uchee..." (2 page carbon copy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Everitt-Vanderbilt family history (1 ms. page) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Crawford family history (1 typescript page) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Townsend family history (1 ms. page) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Nimmons family history (1 ms. page) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - "Holland Nimmons McTyeire," 8-page typescript address delivered by Rev. John J. Lafferty, with notes in pencil and ink by Elizabeth Baskervill Wall, 24 February 1889 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Papers of Janie McTyeire Baskervill
  - Family and V.U.-related Manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - Notes for life of Holland N. McTyeire (10 assorted ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - "Mrs. Frank A. Vanderbilt" (24 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - "Amelia McTyeire Tigert. In Memoriam" (9 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - "Our Sister, Mary Gayle McTyeire Hamilton" (9 assorted ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - Fragment, on life of William Malone Baskervill (1 ms. page) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - Notes on life of John McTyeire (father of H.N. McTyeire) (2 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - Fragment, draft of letter on McTyeire-Vanderbilt connection and founding of University (2 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - 3 lines of verse on books (quote) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)